So here we have our container which is set to grid.
لدينا هذه الحاوية وتم ضبطها على خاصية العرض شبكة.
Let's make it as wide as possible.
لنزيد من عرضها قدر الإمكان.
As you're used to, we have grid template rows and grid template columns,
لدينا هنا صفوف قالب الشبكة وأعمدة قالب الشبكة،
followed by a grid gap.
يليها فراغ الشبكة.
The new part here is grid template areas.
هذا الجزء الجديد هنا هو مناطق قالب الشبكة (grid template areas).
For this grid template area,
فيما يخص منطقة قالب الشبكة،
I've simply used top top,
استخدمت خاصية الوضع الرأسي علوي علوي
bottom left, bottom right.
وهنا للأسفل في الجهة اليمنى والسفلى.
Now, here we can see I've given each of the elements an id.
أما هنا فنلاحظ أني أسندت معرّفًا لكل عنصر.
This id can be used to put each of these elements into the place on the grid we want.
يمكن استخدام هذا المعرف لوضع كل عنصر في المكان الذي نريد على الشبكة.
So for example, if I want let's say box 1 to be on top all the way,
فمثلًا، إذا أردنا أن يبقى المربع واحد في الأعلى دومًا،
I can just say grid area top which is
نضبط منطقة الشبكة على خاصية علوي
defined here as taking up two columns on the top row,
والمعرّفة هنا بعمودين في الصف العلوي،
and then I'm going to put two on the bottom left
ثم سأضع المربع 2 في الجهة السفلية اليسرى،
and three on the bottom right boom.
والمربع 3 في الجهة السفلية اليمنى.
There you can see. In our top,
كما نرى. في الأعلى،
we have box 1,
لدينا المربع واحد،
which is going across both the columns in the first row.
والذي يمتد عرضيًا عبر العمودين في الصف الأول.
Here we have grid template area's top top,
وذلك لأن منطقة قالب الشبكة مضبوطة على: علوي علوي،
and then box two which has been put on the bottom left if here on the bottom left,
والمربع اثنان على وضعية الجهة السفلية اليسرى، ويظهر هنا في الأسفل إلى اليسار،
and three is here on the bottom right.
والمربع ثلاثة في الجهة السفلية اليمنى.
It's very easy to switch these around.
من السهل جدَا تبديل مواقع هذه العناصر.
So we could just say actually we want one on the bottom left,
يمكننا مثلًا أن نقول بأننا نريد الرقم واحد في الجهة السفلية اليسرى،
and we want two on the top.
واثنان في الأعلى.
Now we have box 2 on the top,
أصبح المربع اثنان في الأعلى،
box 1 on the bottom left,
وواحد في الجهة السفلية اليسرى،
and box 3 on the bottom right.
وثلاثة في الجهة السفلية اليمنى.
This is an example of using named grid areas in order to create your master layout.
هذا مثال على استخدام مناطق الشبكة المسماة لإنشاء المخطط الرئيسي.
But this is just a basic example.
ولكن هذا مجرد مثال بسيط.
Let's take a look at one that maybe has a little more practical.
لنلق نظرة على مثال عملي أكثر.
Here you can see I've set up what could be the wire frame for a very basic blog.
ترون هنا أنني أعددت ما قد يمثل إطارًا هيكليًا لمدونة ذات بسيطة أساسية للغاية.
We have a header, a sidebar,
لدينا رأس الصفحة وشريط جانبي
content, and a footer.
ومحتوى الصفحة والتذييل.
Here, I've set up my grid template columns,
هنا ضبطت خاصية أعمدة قالب الشبكة،
my grid template rows.
وخاصية صفوف قالب الشبكة.
Now in grid template areas,
أما خاصية مناطق قالب الشبكة
I've set up a grid that actually uses 1,
فضبطتها لشبكة تستخدم 1،
2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
2, 3, 4, 5, 6,
7, 8 columns across.
7،8 أعمدة أفقيًا.
As you'll notice, it's eight columns across on each line 1,
كما تلاحظون، هناك ثمانية أعمدة في كل سطر، هذا 1،
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8.
It's very important that when making named grid template areas,
من المهم للغاية عند إعداد تسمية مناطق قالب الشبكة
you have to stay consistent.
أن نحافظ على الاتساق.
So you can't have three columns on
فلا يمكن أن يكون هناك ثلاثة أعمدة في
the first row without matching it to the second and the third.
الصف الأول دون مطابقتها مع الصف الثاني والثالث.
Here we can see we've given each of them a grid
نلاحظ أننا خصصنا لكل منها منطقة في الشبكة
area corresponding to the grid that we've set up.
وفقًا للشبكة التي ضبطنا خصائصها.
So we have our header going all the way across,
ولهذا نرى رأس الصفحة تمتد على عرض الشبكة
sidebar here, and then our main is in content.
الشريط الجانبي هنا، والقسم الرئيسي هو المحتوى.
So one issue you may have noticed is that
ربما لاحظتم أن
our sidebar was actually taking up more room than our content here,
الشريط الجانبي يشغل مساحة أكبر من المحتوى،
which is an issue with the way that we have set up the columns.
وذلك نتيجة طريقة ضبطنا للأعمدة.
So what I've done in the code is I've come back to the columns,
لكن بعد تعديل البرمجية، إذا عدنا ثانية إلى الأعمدة،
and I've set it so that our first column is just 30
نجد أن العمود الأول ضُبط بعرض 30
pixels wide which are sidebar stretching across,
بيكسل وهو عرض الشريط الجانبي
and then our second column is 300 pixels wide.
والعمود الثاني بعرض 300 بيكسل.
So we can see here that the only one that this divides up is our sidebar and content.
يمكن أن نلاحظ أن الجزء الوحيد الذي جرى تقسيمه هنا هو الشريط الجانبي والمحتوى.
Because here we have our header stretching across the whole entire top,
لأن رأس الصفحة يمتد عبر الجزء العلوي بالكامل
and our footer stretching across the whole entire bottom.
والتذييل يمتد عبر الجزء السفلي بالكامل.
Another thing that I think we can do we'll find out together is we could change our grid
ومن الأمور الأخرى التي يمكن تعلمها هي كيفية تغيير الشبكة
here so that our main-content took up more of the grid that we set up.
نلاحظ أن المحتوى الرئيسي يحتل الجزء الأكبر من الشبكة التي أعددناها
That works very well.
هذا ممتاز.
Now we can see that the sidebar is taking up even less room,
نلاحظ أن الشريط الجانبي أصبح يحتل مساحة أقل،
and maybe what we want to do is only give it one column in our location setup.
ويمكننا أن نخصص له عمودًا واحدًا عند ضبط الموقع.
Maybe we want to keep it at two.
وقد نرغب بإبقائه ضمن عمودين.
So this is how you can use CSS grid with
هذه طريقة استخدام شبكة CSS
grid template areas to create your own custom layouts.
وخاصية مناطق قالب الشبكة لضبط مخطط الصفحة وفق مواصفات خاصة
Coming up in the next lessons,
في الدروس القادمة،
we're going to look at how to fill out some of the content in
سنتحدث عن كيفية تعبئة بعض المحتوى هنا
here to create first your own blog page,
لإنشاء أول صفحة من مدونتك،
and then second a series of linked pages to individual posts.
ثم سنتحدث عن سلسلة من الصفحات المرتبطة بمنشورات فردية.
This is made so much easier by creating a head
سيكون هذا سهلًا جديدًا عند إنشاء المخططات
of time layouts with CSS grid for each page.
مسبقًا باستخدام شبكة CSS لكل صفحة.
Let's learn more about what that could look like.
سنعرف المزيد عن هذا الأمر بالدروس القادمة.